Henry L. Abbot Family Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Henry L. Abbot Family Papers 1770-2001 (bulk 1832-1870)
MSS84936
Abbot, Henry L.
2,000 items 9 containers plus 3 artifact containers and 1 oversize 5.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Correspondence, memoirs, diaries, writings, photographs, legal and financial records, genealogical material, military records, printed matter, and mementos primarily documenting the professional and family activities of Henry L. Abbot and his family during the Civil War.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Abbot, Edward Stanley, 1841-1863.; Abbot, Fanny Larcom, 1807-1883--Correspondence.; Abbot, Frederic V. (Frederic Vaughan), 1858-1928.; Abbot, Henry L.; Abbot, Jos. Hale (Joseph Hale), 1802-1873--Correspondence.; Abbot, Mary Susan Everett, 1832-1871--Correspondence.; Abbott family--Correspondence.; Everett, Emily, b. 1799.; Grant, Ulysses S. (Ulysses Simpson), 1822-1885.; Larcom, Henry, 1777-1862.; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865.; McClellan, George Brinton, 1826-1885.; Seward, William Henry, 1801-1872--Correspondence.
Organizations
Margaret (Ship); United States. Army --Ordnance and ordnance stores.; United States. Army. Corps of Engineers.; United States. President (1861-1865: Lincoln). Emancipation Proclamation.
Subjects
Bull Run, 1st Battle of, Va., 1861.; Fortification--Washington (D.C.)--History--19th century.; Gettysburg, Battle of, Gettysburg, Pa., 1863.; Napoleonic Wars, 1800-1815.; Peninsular Campaign, 1862.
Places
Cambridge (Mass.)--Social life and customs--19th century.; Massachusetts--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Petersburg (Va.)--History--Siege, 1864-1865.; Richmond (Va.)--History--Siege, 1864-1865.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Artillery operations.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Campaigns.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Causes.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Participation, African American.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Technology.; United States--Politics and government--1861-1865.; Virginia--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Campaigns.; Washington (D.C.)--Social life and customs--19th century.
Occupations
Army officers.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of the Henry L. Abbot family were given to the Library of Congress by Roger Anderson in 2002. Additional material was purchased in 2003.
Transfers
Daguerreotypes, prints, an oil painting, and most photographs have been transferred to the Library's Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of these papers.
Related Materials
In addition to Abbot’s diaries and papers held in the
Houghton Library at Harvard University
, other related material is also at the
Oregon Historical Society in Portland
.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Henry L. Abbot Family are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Henry L. Abbot
Date Event
1831, Aug. 13 Born, Beverly, Mass.
1854 Graduated second in his class, United States Military Academy, West Point, N.Y.
1854-1855 Second lieutenant, United States Corps of Topographical Engineers, Office of Pacific Railroad Explorations, Washington, D.C.
1855 Assisted in railroad survey in California and Oregon
1856 Married Mary Susan Everett (died 1871)
1857 First lieutenant, United States Corps of Topographical Engineers
1857-1861 Assisted Captain Andrew A. Humphreys on survey of the Mississippi River delta and coauthored their Report upon the Physics and Hydraulics of the Mississippi River (1861)
1861-1862 Assistant topographical engineer, staff of General Irvin McDowell, United States Army Wounded at the First Battle of Bull Run, Va. Assisted General John G. Barnard, chief engineer for the Department of Washington, in constructing forts south of the Potomac River Aide-de-camp to General Barnard in the Peninsular Campaign, Va. Chief topographical engineer for Major General Nathaniel Banks’s expedition to New Orleans, La.
1863-1865 Colonel, First Connecticut Artillery, United States Volunteers, in defense of Washington, D.C. Captain, Corps of Engineers, United States Army Commanded siege artillery for United States armies operating against Petersburg and Richmond, Va.
1865 Mustered out of the volunteer service with brevet rank of major general and returned to regular duty in the Corps of Engineers with rank of major
1866-1886 Colonel, Corps of Engineers, United States Army
1888-1895 Member, Board of Ordnance and Fortifications, United States Department of War
1895 Retired from active service
1897-1904 Member, technical committee, and consulting engineer, La Compagnie Nouvelle du Canal de Panama (New Panama Canal Co.)
1904 Brigadier general, United States Army, retired, by Act of Congress
1905-1906 Member, board of consulting engineers appointed by President Theodore Roosevelt to prepare plans for the Panama Canal
1905-1910 Professor of hydraulic engineering, George Washington University, Washington, D.C.
1927, Oct. 1 Died, Cambridge, Mass.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of the family of Henry Larcom Abbot (1831-1927) span the years 1770-2001, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1832-1870. Correspondence, diaries, memoirs, military records, financial and legal records, genealogical material, photographs, writings, clippings, and mementos comprise the major part of the collection. The material is arranged alphabetically by type of material or name of creator and chronologically thereunder. Artifacts and oversize material are arranged and described according to the containers and folders from which the items were removed.
Correspondence, diaries, and memoirs of Henry L. Abbot and other family members constitute the core of the collection. Most of the letters were exchanged between Abbot and his wife, Mary Susan (“Susie”) Everett Abbot, and mother, Fanny Larcom Abbot, and reflect primarily his service in the Union army and family and social activities in Massachusetts during the Civil War. A graduate of the United States Military Academy and a career officer in the United States Army Corps of Engineers, Abbot served as a topographical engineer and Union officer throughout the war and earned numerous promotions. He was wounded at the First Battle of Bull Run, assisted with the design and construction of fortifications around the city of Washington, and served in the Peninsular Campaign. In 1863, he was commissioned colonel commanding the First Connecticut Artillery volunteers and led the siege artillery for the Union armies operating against Petersburg and Richmond, Virginia, in 1864-1865. In his letters, Abbot discreetly described movements of the army, concerns about Abraham Lincoln’s administration, African-American soldiers, religion, and Union commanders. His caution was due not only to military exigencies but also to his wife’s admonitions concerning his political differences with her family, apparently ardent abolitionists, who also had access to his letters. Abbot wrote of his achievements and occasionally of the technology of the ordnance he commanded such as larger projectiles that weighed as “much as the cannon of ten years ago.” In a letter dated July 16, 1864, his father Joseph Hale Abbot, a mathematics professor and school principal in Beverly, Massachusetts, discussed causes of the war, Lincoln’s Emancipation Proclamation, Ulysses S. Grant’s situation in Virginia, and the presidential aspirations of General George McClellan.
Letters from Henry L. Abbot’s mother and wife focus on family matters and the childhood activities of his son Frederic V. Abbot. Letters also discuss the death of Abbot’s brother Edward Stanley Abbot in action at Gettysburg in 1863 and social receptions in Washington, D.C., in the 1850s, including a description of William Wilson Corcoran’s greenhouse and gallery of paintings.
Diaries and memoirs in the collection include reminiscences by Emily Everett, Henry L. Abbot’s mother-in-law. A resident of Cambridge, Massachusetts, her memoirs span most of the nineteenth century with family vignettes such as helping her grandfather adjust his powdered wigs, town personalities, childhood adventures, births, and deaths. The collection also contains a journal by Abbot’s mother recording his childhood development from 1832 to 1840 and photocopies of Abbot’s Civil War diaries for 1864-1865, including his detailed index to his diaries now in the Houghton Library of Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts.
Mementos, ships logs, maps, and biographical material comprise a file pertaining to Henry Larcom, shipmaster and Abbot’s maternal grandfather. Most of the items relate to Larcom’s survival of the wreck of the Margaret (ship) in the Atlantic Ocean in 1810. Ensnared in the confiscation of American shipping by the French during the Napoleonic Wars, Larcom and his vessel had been detained by French authorities in Naples. Unable to secure release of his vessel or its cargo, Larcom and several other American masters were permitted to return to Massachusetts on the Margaret. The ship capsized in a squall in the middle of the Atlantic, and Larcom survived over a month on the open sea before his rescue by a passing vessel. The actions of the crew during the ordeal were questioned by survivors, and several accounts of the incident are in the biographical material. Printed matter includes a recollection of the event by his daughter, Fanny Larcom Abbot, published in 1871. A shawl, rope, and kerchief salvaged by Larcom from the wreck, a pocketknife, a bound nautical volume, a “burning glass,” and a wallet comprise the mementos.
Although Henry L. Abbot published extensively in various technical journals and books, only a few of his writings are contained in the collection. His survey of the Mississippi River delta, Report upon the Physics and Hydraulics of the Mississippi River coauthored with Andrew A. Humphreys, was translated and reproduced throughout Europe. The collection includes an Italian review of the report with a congratulatory letter from William Henry Seward, secretary of state, and a commemorative centennial reissue by the Corps of Engineers in 1961. An unidentified notebook, circa 1828, with numerous stories, poems, and commentary is contained among the miscellaneous writings.
Arrangement of the Papers
The collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material or name of creator and chronologically thereunder. Artifacts and oversize material are arranged and described according to the containers and folders from which the items were removed.
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm2002084936
Container List
- Biographical material (Box 1)
  - Abbot, Frederic V., 1922-1928, undated (Box 1)
  - Abbot, Henry L., 1850, 1913-1952, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
- Broadsides and certificates, 1865, 1913, 1925 See Oversize (Box 1)
- Clippings, 1850, 1864, 1902-1905, 1923-1992, undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1849-1869, (13 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1870-1963, undated, (4 folders) (Box 2)
- Diaries and memoirs (Box 2)
  - Abbot, Charles Greeley, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Abbot, Fanny Larcom, 1832-1840, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Abbot, Henry L. (photocopies) (Box 2)
    - Index, 1850-1918 (Box 2)
    - 1864, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - 1865, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Abbot, Marion (“May”) Stanley, 1895 (Box 3)
  - Everett, Emily, 1816, 1887-1890, 1905 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - 1807, 1844 (Box 3)
    - 1949, undated (Box 4)
- Financial and legal records, 1828, 1849, 1861-1922, 1941-1989, (2 folders) (Box 4)
- Genealogy (Box 4)
  - Notes, 1851-1941, undated See also Oversize, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Printed matter (Box 4)
    - 1847, 1876 (Box 4)
    - 1902, 1906, 1925, (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - Slave records, 1814 (Box 6)
- Larcum, Henry (Box 6)
  - Biographical material, 1817, 1903, 1968, undated, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Logbook, Betsy (ship), 1800 (Box 6)
  - Lunar observations and journal, Rover (schooner), 1816-1821 (Box 6)
  - Maps, 1981, undated See also Oversize (Box 6)
  - Mementos, circa 1810, 1847, undated See Artifacts (Box 6)
  - Miscellany, 1869, undated (Box 6)
  - Navigation notebooks, 1770, 1796, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Printed matter, 1809, 1844, 1871, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Shipping invoices, 1819 (Box 7)
- Mementos (Box 7)
  - Lincoln, Abraham, 1865, undated See Artifacts (Box 7)
  - Military insignia and medals, 1865, 1918, undated See Artifacts (Box 7)
  - Military reunions, badges, 1886-1916 See Artifacts (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous, 1782, 1872, 1930-1932, undated See also Artifacts (Box 7)
- Memorials, 1813, 1828, 1847, 1865, 1928-1929 (Box 7)
- Military records (Box 7)
  - Abbot, Frederic V., 1919-1920, undated (Box 7)
  - Abbot, Henry L., extracts from The War of the Rebellion re Abbot, 1861-1865 (Box 7)
    - Set I (Box 7)
    - Set II (Box 7)
      - Vols. 1-2 (Box 7)
      - Vols. 3-4 and Addenda, (3 folders) (Box 8)
  - History of the First Connecticut Artillery and of the Siege Trains of the Armies Operating against Richmond, 1862-1865, 1893 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
    - Extract from Board of Engineers report re Fort Carroll, Md., 1864 (Box 8)
    - “Notes on the Status of the Corps of Engineers,” 1885 (Box 8)
    - Petersburg National Military Park, Va., 1951 (Box 8)
- Writings (Box 9)
  - Book, Family Letters of General Henry Larcom Abbot, by Catherine C. Abbot (Box 9)
    - Correspondence and notes, 1928-1994, undated (Box 9)
    - Drawings, undated (Box 9)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 9)
    - Text, 2001 (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
    - Abbot, Charles Greeley, 1930-1966, undated (Box 9)
    - Abbot, Henry L., 1861-1864, 1912, undated, (3 folders) (Box 9)
    - Others, circa 1828, 1840, 1861, 1953, 1960, (2 folders) (Box 9)
  - Poetry, 1852, 1863, undated (Box 9)
- Artifacts (Box VA 1)
  - Larcom, Henry (Box VA 1)
    - Mementos (Box VA 1)
      - circa 1810 (Container 6) (Box VA 1)
      - 1847, undated (Container 6), (3 folders) (Box VA 2)
  - Mementos (Box VA 2)
    - Lincoln, Abraham, 1865, undated (Container 7), (2 folders) (Box VA 2)
    - Military insignia and medals, 1865, 1918, undated (Container 7) (Box VA 2)
    - Military reunions, badges, 1886-1916 (Container 7) (Box VA 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 1782, 1876, undated (Container 7) (Box VA 3)
- Oversize (Box OV 1)
  - Broadsides and certificates, 1865, 1913, 1925 (Container 1) (Box OV 1)
  - Genealogical notes (Box OV 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box OV 1)
      - Chart, undated (Container 4) (Box OV 1)
  - Larcom, Henry (Box OV 1)
    - Maps (Box OV 1)
      - North Atlantic Ocean, 1821 (Container 6) (Box OV 1)